## Manuel Duarte de Vasconcelos Silva

#### **Contact:**

SIM -Dpto Física FCUL, Campo Grande, Edifício C8, Piso 5, lab 8.5.02 1749-016 Lisboa Portugal Mobile: +351 96 4525553

E-mail: msilva@sim.ul.pt

www.linkedin.com/in/manuel-silva-5191b5149

## Personal profile

For the past four years I have worked as a researcher at CENTRA/SIM (Multidisciplinary Centre for Astrophysics <a href="https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/">https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/</a>). The focus of my work has been the development of Data Mining/Machine Learning tools, particularly Bayesian inference models, for scientific exploitation of large datasets from the Gaia mission of the European Space Agency (ESA). I have also worked with code for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics in the context of the OPTICON project. Prior to this I was a PhD researcher, modelling the spiral arms of our own Galaxy as traced by runaway stars¹.

### **Projects**

2014 – 2017	Opticon – "Optical Infrared Co-ordination Network for Astronomy"
	Development and testing of software for PSF reconstruction in A

 Development and testing of software for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics (GLAO), in the context of the MUSE-GALACSI instrument

# Gaia: National Participation in the Data Processing and Analysis Consortium (DPAC)

 Development of data mining/machine learning software for estimation of stellar parameters in large databases in the context of the European Space Agency's (ESA) mission Gaia

#### **Positions**

2013 - 2014

2013 – Present	Researcher
	CENTRA/SIM (https://centra.tecnico.ulisboa.pt/), Portugal
2012	Researcher
	University of Hertfordshire, UK
2006	Sales consultant
	Portugal Telecom, Portugal

#### **Education**

## 2007 – 2011 PhD in Astrophysics – University of Herfordshire, UK

- Thesis: Runaway Stars in the Galactic Halo: Their Origin and Kinematics
- Supervisor: Dr Ralf Napiwotzki

<sup>1</sup> http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21729044.000

#### 2004 - 2006

#### Master degree in Statistics - Universidade do Porto, Portugal

- Thesis: *Um processo de risco perturbado: aproximações numéricas à probabilidade de ruína*
- Supervisor: Dra Margarida Brito
- Topics:
  - Stochastic processes
  - Machine learning
  - Multivariate statistics
- Final grade: "Muito Bom" (Very Good)

### 1998 - 2004

# First degree in Astrophysics (Physics/Applied Mathematics) – Universidade do Porto, Portugal

Final grade: 13

#### **Publications**

[1] Silva M. D. V. & Napiwotzki R., "High Galactic latitude runaway stars as tracers of the spiral arms", 2013, MNRAS, 431, 502-510 – Astro-ph: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1302.0761v1">http://arxiv.org/abs/1302.0761v1</a>

[2] Napiwotzki R. & Silva M. D. V., "Runaway and hypervelocity stars. The supernova connection", 2012, MEMORIE della Società Astronomica Italiana – Astro-ph: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1109.4116">http://arxiv.org/abs/1109.4116</a>

[3] Silva M. D. V. & Napiwotzki R., "Ejection velocities of high Galactic latitude runaway stars", 2011, MNRAS, 411, 2596 – Astro-ph: <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.3651">http://arxiv.org/abs/1010.3651</a>

#### IT skills

#### General:

- OS administration/scripting (Linux and Windows)
- Git/Github
- Visual Studio Code
- misc. applications: Tex, Gimp, Photoshop, MS Office (Word, Excel, Access)

## Developed packages:

- rpsfpy: software in Python for PSF reconstruction in Adaptive Optics
- Pysysp: Python package for synthetic stellar photometry: <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pysysp/1.0.1">https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pysysp/1.0.1</a>
- MASS: Massive MCMC sampler (Bayesian inference): <a href="https://github.com/mdusilva/mass">https://github.com/mdusilva/mass</a>
- Mamuto: Python package for distributed computing in clusters: <a href="https://github.com/mdusilva/mamuto">https://github.com/mdusilva/mamuto</a>

#### **Programming:**

- Python, R, MATLAB, Fortran 90, C++ (basic level)
- parallel/distributed computing: Spark, MPI

#### **Databases:**

• Postgre SQL, SQLite, Python-SQL, PL/SQL

#### Web:

HTML, CSS, Jekyll, Apache Web servers (configuration)

## Python:

- Data Science: scikit-learn, Pandas, SPAMS (dictionary learning)
- distributed computing: execute, pyspark
- Bayesian inference (MCMC): pymc

## Languages

Fluent: Portuguese, English Good understanding: French, Spanish

Basic Greek and German (level A1 certificate)

## Other interests

I am a qualified Futsal referee. I like to play Football and Futsal, playing chess, Philosophy, travelling. I am also engaged in Science outreach activities directed at the general public.